in this video we're going to make a
turn-based grid combat system in unity
our units will be in two teams placed in
a grid with a certain move radius and
the ability to do attacks each units
won't do its move and then its attack in
a turn-by-turn bastes let's begin
[Music]
hello and welcome I'm your code monkey
and this channel is all about helping
you learn how to make your own games
with NF tutorials made by a professional
indie game developer so if you find the
video helpful consider subscribing okay
so here's what we want to make over here
we have a nice map with a bunch of
characters so these are on the blue team
and these are on the red team
now it's turn-based so right now the
active turn is for this unit on the grid
we can visually see how far he can move
so I can click on any of these valid
grid positions I click any of there you
go he moves towards it now for each turn
I can do one movement and one attack so
over here is an enemy and I can click on
him to attack so if I click yep there
you go it does an attack and now for
this system I went to the design of one
character at a time rather than one
phone teamed and one full team so as
soon as the character on the pool team
finished it picked a character from the
red team so now it's this one and again
I can see how far I can move note how
the movement is using pathfinding so
because this creighton here is walking I
cannot actually reach that position but
again I can move anywhere that I want so
let's go all the way up there and now I
can attack so let's attack that one and
yep there you go now it's back into the
blue team and again I can move and now
that one is too far so I cannot attack
him so I can press space in order to
skip my turn and now it's back into this
one and now this one I can try moving in
there now try hitting him and no piece
too far so now skip again and so on and
so forth so here is a base for a nice
turn-based great combat system
everything is functional and we couldn't
later expand upon this with some special
abilities and some AI for the enemies to
make a game pretty much like X huh right
now there's a spring sale happening on
the assets or turns of great assets
icons sound effects and awesome tools at
a great discount use them to make your
game really stand out check it out by
clicking the link in the description and
if you pick up anything through there
you'll also be helping out the channel
alright so this circle let's get to it
okay so here's our starting scene we
have a map with some units and some
objects now the map is built using the
grid system that we made in a previous
video so I can turn on gizmos and
visualize the grid I'm also using the
pathfinding which again was also made in
another video and I'm also using the
town map which we're going to use to
display our reach
about areas so if you haven't seen those
videos then check the links in the
description this combat system won't be
built on top of those which once again
is a great showcase of the power of
writing clean code so we made that grid
system a long time ago and we've reused
it in so many different scenarios
because we made sure to write our code
in a clean and reusable way here in the
editor there's a simple game object and
has this script attached to it so this
is a script that is setting up the grid
the path finding and eat Alma here is
the script and it's pretty simple we
just define a certain map weight and map
height then we construct our grid our
grid pathfinding and our movement town
map so with those systems in place we
have our nice base this video is made
possible thanks to these awesome
supporters go to patreon.com/scishow to
code monkey to get some perks and help
keep the videos free for everyone now
let's make our grid combat system we're
going to first work with a single unit
and give it a simple move order so in
the project funds let's create an EC
JavaScript call this our grid combat
system let's make a game object to run
it and attach our script okay now in
here let's first make a field to add our
unit reference so we make a sterilized
film of type unit for it combat we're
going to see how that class is set up in
a bit so we have film for a unit and
back in the editor over here we can now
simply drag our reference okay so first
of all let's make some simple movements
sending a unit to a target position now
each unit is based off of this prefab
here so the end has a main unit great
combat script and the rest of the end of
the setup like we did in the modular
character controller system so it has a
bunch of modules like this one here
which moves the unit towards a target
position using plat finding and this one
is moving to unity by modifying the
rigidbody velocity but essentially for
the logic of our combat system all we
need is the main script in here and this
script is already set up to interact
with all the rest so in our unit great
combat script on we really care about
right now is the ability to call this
function so we moved to a Terry position
and we have a comeback alright so let's
go back into our main script here we are
and let's do a simple voi update and on
the update let's test for
left mouse button play so when the left
mouse button is down in here and let's
grab the mouse wrong position so for
that there's a function in the utilities
which is long as you can download for
free from me in Tacoma com
so I can go into the Tonys to get the
mods wrong position here is the function
in case you want to write it yourself
now with the mouse wrong position let's
down the unit to go there so going to
the unit credit combat and we use that
function we saw tell me to move to the
target Mouser opposition all right so
just like this it should work let's test
okay here we are with all the units idle
and now I move my mouse and I press the
unlit mouse button any of there you go
the unit correctly went into that
position and now if I click behind that
crate and yep there you go as you can
see it is indeed using path line alright
so we have our basic movement working
awesome now one of the main things that
we want to apply to our combat system is
to have some limited movement so the
unit cannot for example move an Internet
month so I cannot come in there and he
should not be able to move this whole
distance so back in our code here let's
calculate all the valid positions that
unit can actually move to now the way
we're going to do that is to come late
the path to each position and then we're
going to check the length of that path
so let's write that code on our start
and for testing let's start off small so
let's say our unit can only move at most
five steps and now in here we want to
test all the positions within that
radius so first we get the unit and we
access its position but now we don't
want the worm position but rather its
position on the grid so for that we need
to access the grid again the grid is
being set up in this script so it's in
here and it's being constructed in here
and we already have a nice simple
function to return that grid so let's
access this function so we go into that
script access the static instance and
get our grid so using the grid we can
access the function in order to get the
x and y position of a certain world
position
so we get the unit ex in the unit wine
now with the units x and y we can simply
do a basic cycle so we do a four we
start off with the X start off at unit X
minus Emacs move distance and we're
going to go until the X is under unit X
plus D max move distance and do the same
thing for the Y alright so here we are
cycling through all the grid positions
there are around our unit position
within a certain maximum distance now
first let's check if this position is
walkable so for that we need to access
the tough finding grid so the position
is either walkable or not walkable now
if it is well cable then let's complete
the path to that position so if there is
a valid path then we get the actual path
test account so if we get the path we
calculate the path count towards the
maximum distance and it's either within
the move distance or it's outside our
move distance so if it's in here then
it's valid if it's any of these others
then it's invalid all right so our logic
should be working now in order to
visually see it we can use the town map
now here in the actor I've already set
up my town map it's prepared using two
towel types so there's none which is
invisible and move which means we can
move towards it over here we can use
that we get the movement on map and we
set this town map sprite and we get this
X and this Y in this case set it to move
and all the others we set it to
invisible
all right so just like this everything
should be working we should be able to
visually see all the great positions
that we can move to and all the ones we
can't all right so let's test any up
right away we can see that our logic is
indeed working so we can see which valid
positions we can move to and we can see
which ones are within our max range of
five of our actual unit now let's just
verify that everything is actually
working correctly so here let's place
some more crates and if there it is just
like that we can see that it is indeed
working so these crates are plugging so
we can no longer move to this area all
right so we can now validate all of our
possible move positions awesome now we
need to make sure that we can only
actually move towards the valley move
position because right now visually we
can see it but I can self like in here
and Yap he goes in there so let's do
just that now one of the best things
that we added when we made our grid
system was the ability to make it work
with generics so each grid position has
a grid object of a specific type now so
far we've been using this empty word
object so really just stores the create
the X&Y and then we're doing some debug
drawn lines so we can visually see the
grid now let's replace this with a
proper grid object to store all the data
that we want so let's copy this class
then let's go into the combat system and
then you know let's create it all right
so we have our basic red object in here
and now we need to do over here is
modify the type instead of using this
time let's use the one on the grid
combat system all right everything is
working correctly and now in this grid
object well it's all of the data that
we're going to need so for example let's
have one a simple private ball for is
Valley blue position and some functions
is set it
all right we have our simple bullion and
now all the way appear when we are
completing our valid positions if it is
valid then we go into our grid in order
to get the grid object on this X Y and
we call our set function and in this
case this one is true and then on the
other case it's false so let's do that
up here okay so we set them all as
invalid then we go through and the ones
that are valid we set them to Val so now
that we have validated our move
positions let's go down here on our unit
grid combat instead of moving it
directly to there let's first validate
that position so we access our grid we
have the grid object on the mouse wheel
on position we check if it is a valid
move position and if so then we do tell
our unit to move towards that position
okay so just like this it should be
working
let's test so here we are let's try
clicking in an invalid position so out
here I click and nope nothing happens
the unit does not move now I click in a
valid position any of there we go he
goes towards that position all right so
our logic is working awesome so here we
have our grid movement being correctly
validated except right now we're only
calculating it on start so as my unit
moves it should update the actual
newfound position so let's do just that
first we take all this code and we
actually make it into a proper function
so instead of being on the start so we
have our update from with move positions
function and then on our start we call
that function and now here on our update
we need to call it also when the unit
reaches its position and we should also
block our movement once the unit is
actually moving so for that let's make a
simple state machine just like we did in
the enemy AI video
all right so we have a simple I known
for our state and if you want to store
that then on a weekly serif as its state
dot normal and on update we do is switch
on our state if we are normal then don't
listen to inputs and if we are on
waiting then we are simply waiting so
now I mean here when we turn to move
let's modify the state and in this case
we're going to put it state waiting and
then this move to function already has a
comeback that gets called when the unit
reaches its position it's just a simple
action don't get I cover delegates in
another video if you want to learn more
but essentially this function won't get
triggered at the end so it's in here
that we can reset the state back into
state dot normal and after resetting the
state then we can update our valid move
positions all right so that should do it
let's test ok so here we are and we can
see all of our move positions now let's
move down here and wait any of the Rio s
and this gets there now he updates now I
can move to these positions so let's go
in here and yep it updates and now I can
go in here and there you go now the
validation is working so I click out
here and nope it does not go anywhere so
clean there and yep there he goes all
right so everything is working awesome
so we already have quite a lot of our
system we already have our unit moving
in a grid and it's moving in a
turn-by-turn basis so after I move I
cannot click anywhere I have to wait for
the unit to get there and only then can
I actually move again so our turn logic
is already working and while so
validating just how far you can move so
I cannot move this unit all the way
appear only into the valid move
positions so without working now let's
set up our attacking so we want to be
able to click on an enemy in order to
attack him if he is within range
so first let's handle clicking on it now
one way we can do that is using
colliders and great casts in order to
choose the enemy to attack however using
that approach would mean that the
collider size would have to perfectly
match the annoying grid size so instead
of colliders and Ray casts a simpler way
we can do is simply store our unit on
the grid object itself so here in the
grid object that we made we can simply
add another field and this will be a
film for the unit that is actually
standing on this grid object so we add
of time
quit combat and it's UniCredit combat
that is on top of this great object and
now some function to set and get alright
so we have our field and then a function
to set a function to clear and a
function to get it so now we need to
initialize this so let's go all the way
up here and we're going to add another
serialize field and this won't be an
array of our unit for combat and now
let's go into the editor and in here
let's drag all of our unit references
okay there they are
and now in here on our start let's
update all of our grid objects so let's
second through it so we cycle through
all of our units and we get the grill
get the grid object on that units
position and we set that field okay so
now down here we can check when we click
on a unit position so we get our grid
then we get the grid object underneath
the mouse and then we check if there is
a unit inside of that grid object if so
then that means we have clicked on top
of the unit then we test if the target
unit is an enemy to the current one so
we clicked on an enemy of the current
unit and if so then we want to attack
him so we tell the this unit in order to
attack the other unit and again the
attack also has a delegate that triggers
on the attack complete so we can do the
same thing to modify our state so he
attacks a target in it then he goes back
to normal and then we have our not an
enemy and not a unit here so if we
attack then we break and if not then we
keep going down here and we test for
simple movement all right so just like
this should be working so if we click on
an enemy we should be able to attack him
let's test ok so here we are and if I
click outside move area no cannot move I
click yep I still got some right more
movement now if I click on top
an enemy if there you go he correctly
attacks the enemy and effect me I'm
talking to himself nope doesn't do
anything click on top of and mi and nope
does not do anything alright so I can
now click on an enemy in order to attack
him great now we still have a few things
to note so first it's we also need to
validate the attack range so right now
this one is very far but I can still
click in order to attack him and when we
move we need to actually update the
underlying grid object since right now
I've moved this unit but the underlying
grid object so has this unit placed on
its actual starting position so let's do
both notes first for the attack we just
need to use the function that checks if
it can attack so if this unit that can
attack the target unit so you can either
attack or cannot attack and this
function is wrong just doing a basic
vector three distance and in here if we
cannot attack and let's spawn a simple
pop-up all right that should do it
and now for updating the grid down here
when we have a valid move position what
we're going to do is remove them from
the current position so we go into the
bread we get the grid object of this
unit and then we clear that in acrid
combat then we take the target grid
object and then we set the unified
combat to this one all right so that's
it
let's see if our attack is working ok
here we are know the attack distance is
pretty much the same as the move
distance so if I come like he should not
attack so quick and nope cannot attack
ok great now if I move close to him and
I four click yep there you go now I can
indeed attack him so I can move into a
random position and click any of there
you go everything is validated all right
so here we have movement and attacking
working awesome so here we have our
system almost fully built everything is
working perfectly except it's only
working for a single unit so the very
important thing that we are missing is
our turn system now I already covered a
simple turn-based battle system in a
this video so here let's do something
pretty similar over here in our grid
combat system we already have a nice
array of one of our units now what we
need is to have them split into two
teams and go from one team to the next
one so let's make some simple two lists
so we've got Blue Team and Red Team now
in here when we are cycling through them
we can do that as well all right so very
simple we just initialize our own list
we cycle through and we add them
depending on the team they're in now up
here we're also going to need some
indexes in order to figure out which one
is our active unit and we start them
both off at minus one okay now let's
make a function to select the next
active units so first we check the team
on the current active one so if the
current one is either no or it's on the
red team then we get the next one on the
blue team and if now we get the next one
on the right team so let's make that
function alright so we get the next
active one of this team so we just
increment our index and then we return
that one on that position and then here
when we select we set the unit quick
combat to be done alright so all of our
logic should be working so the first
time that we call this this one won't be
known so it's going to pick one from the
blue team then next time we call then
this one will be on the blue team so
we're going to pick one from the red
team and then so on and so on so we have
this function to correctly pick the next
active character and now most of the
rest of the code already works using
this field so everything else should be
working so we just need to calm this so
peer on our start we set everything and
before we update our available positions
well it's not like the next active unit
and up here and let's no longer expose
this in the editor since it's going to
start off as no okay that should do it
now for testing let's make them swap
after just moving once per turn
so down here we have our movement okay
and after the end finish is moving then
let's some like the next active Vienna
okay let's test and here we are in it's
this one's turn someone let's move in
here and yep as he gets there now it's
this one's turn and again everything is
being validated so I click all the way
in here nope nothing's now let's move
that one in here and yep that was the
red team and I expected the only team so
the blue team move and the red team move
all right so all the logic is working
and all of the terms are correctly
moving now that our logic is working
let's make them move and attack on the
same turn so in here we can just store
two simple billions when we saw like the
next active one let's set both these to
true and down here we found a time all
right so we found a team move any attack
and now just say function to test if the
turn is over so if we cannot move or
attack then we end this turn and we're
going to do our test
every time that we move or attack so we
can also use this function in order to
skip the turn so here on our update
let's also do a simple input yet key
down when you press space then let's
give our turn all right everything
should be working
let's test so here we are in start off
with this yep so far so good let's try
moving in there and yep he moves now
let's try attacking and if there you an
attack you know it's this one so now
this one I can first attack and then I
move and since I finished now it's this
one so now this one moves and now I try
to attack but I cannot because he's too
far so I can press space and if there
you go I skip the turn and now it's this
one and now this one can move and now
let's attack this one and so on and so
forth all right awesome so all of our
turn logic and all of our combat logic
is correctly working now for just some
punch in here I already have implemented
camera panning so I can press the way s
and E in order to move the camera so
that one is being handled using
Sen machine now I covered how to use sin
machine in a previous video so check it
out if you don't know how to use it
again it's being handled by our normal
game handler script we have our handle
camera movement and then we have a nice
function in order to set the camera fall
position
so just for Polish let's call this one
whenever our turn changes so here when
the turn is over let's go where we
select the next active unit and after
selecting let's go into our game Handler
and call this function to pan the camera
onto our unit all right just like that
let's see okay here we are let's move
this one in here and now let's skip and
if there go the camera pen so that one
now I can move it can skip any up pencil
down and so on alright so here we have
just a bit of nice polish okay so here
we have our system fully working we have
two teams the blue team and the red team
now each unit can move an attack in its
own turn and I can also skip a turn if I
want so I can move this unit then I can
do an attack and after the attack is
finished then now it's a red team's turn
so now I can move an attack and there
you go now it's backing to the blue team
so they change between the red team and
the blue team now for the movement you
can see the event positions that we can
move to all the positions are
accumulated using pathfinding so we can
only move to valid positions so here
this crate is walking so I cannot go
into that position so I can click on a
valid position move in there and now
click in order to attack an enemy and
now the attack right now we set up to
always hit but we could easily add some
sort of hit chance based on distance in
flanking in order to make this pretty
much like X huh so you can click to move
click to attack and if there you go as
soon as it ends it ends its turn now I
can again move an attack and so on now
right now something that could be a
performance bottleneck is how we
calculate all of the possible paths that
the unit can take so depending on how
far your units can move this can be
quite costly or not as much now one way
we can easily solve that is to use the
path finding that we made using unity
dots that one if you remember works
thousands of times faster than this one
so if you wanted to build upon this
system then that's one of the things
that you could actually improve beyond
that here is a fully functioning
turn-based great combat system let me
know in the comments if you'd like to
see me expand upon this
to make a complete game like Exxon this
video is made possible thanks to these
awesome supporters go to
patreon.com/scishow
code monkey to get some perks and help
keep the videos free for everyone as
always you can download the project
found a little is from unity comic calm
subscribe the channel for more unity
tutorials push the nuclear 7 accounts
and I'll see you next time
[Music]